Now today's דף *daf* is ק"י *kuf yud*. We pick up at
the very top of ק"י עמוד א' *kuf yud amud aleph*. We're
discussing the ארבע כוסות kosot *arba kosot*, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is disturbed about the idea of the ארבע כוסות kosos *arba kosot*
because it's pairs, it's even numbers, and we're not supposed to do
things in pairs, presumably that the concern of that it exposes us
to מזיקים mazikim *mazikin*, we'll see later it could also expose us
to people doing witchcraft. So a couple of answers in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, one was that it's ליל שימורים *leil shimurim*, we don't
have to be concerned about those things. The other is that each
one is an independent מצווה *mitzvah*, you don't have to look at
them as pairs.
And another one which we're going to see echoed today also is
that since one of them is the כוס kos ברכת המזון Birkas
Hamazon *kos birkat hamazon*, that does not, that only makes things better,
not worse. So a כוס של ברכה kos shel bracha, *kos shel
bracha* is not מצטרף mitztaref לרעה *mitztaref l'ra'ah*, so it's like you
have three, not four. Interesting that it's only the כוס kos ברכת
המזון Birkas Hamazon *kos birkat hamazon*, I mean you do מצוות *mitzvot*
with the others as well. Anyway, just to let you know, today's
דף *daf* is going to be completely devoted to this issue of
doing things in pairs and the type of
demonic dangers it might expose us to. So let's take a look.
So first we finish the ברייתא braisa, *Baraisa* because the ברייתא *Baraisa*
we quoted says you don't do things in pairs, don't eat in
pairs, don't drink in pairs, not pairs of people, but meaning like
two of the same food, two glasses of wine, you don't wipe
yourself in the bathroom twice, and you don't have sex twice at
night. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so it picks up with
that theme, top of ק"י עמוד א' *kuf yud amud aleph*, לא
יעשה צרכו
תרי *lo ya'aseh tzorcho trei*, you should not do your needs, meaning
have sex twice. So אמאי *amai*, why is that? נמלך הוא *nimlach
hu*, you know, it's a second time, you've,
it's a new decision.
So assuming you do it once and then you're tired out and
then later on in the night you decide again, so it's a
separate act, sort of like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said before about
each כוס kos, *kos* being different, it's not seen as a pair.
So אמר אביי Abaye *amar Abaye*, so אביי Abaye *Abaye* says, הכי
קאמר *hachi ka'amar*, לא יאכל תרי וישתה תרי ולא יעשה צרכו אפילו
פעם אחת *lo yochal trei v'yishteh trei v'lo ya'aseh tzorcho afilu pa'am
achat*. He completely changes the ברייתא *Baraisa*. It's not about don't have
sex twice, it's don't eat twice and drink twice and also don't
have sex right after eating and drinking, like don't go into the
water right after you've eaten. ואם חליש ומתרע *v'im chalish u'mitra*, maybe
you'll get weak and you'll expose and you know and something bad'll
happen. So since we're talking about health, it's another health advice, but
it really is not related to the issue of pairs directly. All
right. תנו רבנן rabbanan, *Tanu rabanan*, the rabbis taught: שותה כפליים *shoteh
keflayim*, if somebody drinks double, like he had two cups of wine,
דמו בראשו *damo b'rosho*, your blood is on your own head as
we would say, your blood is on your head. You're responsible for
anything bad that happens to you. You're exposing yourself to these dangers.
אמר רב Rav. יהודה *amar Rav Yehuda*, רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says,
אימתי *ematay*, when is this true? בזמן שלא ראה פני שוק *bizman
shelo ra pnei shuk*, that's only if you didn't go outdoors in
between each glass of wine, take a little walk around the block.
אבל ראה פני השוק *aval ra pnei hashuk*, if you saw the
marketplace, you went outside between each glass, השוק בידו *hashuk b'yado*, you're
allowed to, then apparently, we would say it helps you walk off
the liquor, the alcohol, but anyway, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* apparently that's
not its concern, but it makes each glass independent so it's no
longer considered to be a pair. אמר רב אשי *amar Rav Ashi*,
so רב אשי *Rav Ashi* says, חזינא ליה לרב חנניה בר אביבי
*chazina leh l'Rav Hananya bar Abibi*, I saw רב חנניה בר אביבי
*Rav Hananya bar Abibi* דעל כל כסא *d'al kol kassa*, on every
glass of wine, הוי נפיק וחזי אפי שוקא *havei nafik v'chazei apei
shuka*, he would go outside, you know, see the marketplace. It's wonder
whether it's explicitly the marketplace or does it just mean like don't
just step one foot out your door, you have to really go
outside anyway, and
and then he would drink as many glasses as he wants as
long as he would interrupt each one with walking outside, fresh air,
exactly. ולא אמרין אלא לצאת לדרך *v'lo amrin ela l'atzis laderech*, and
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is qualifying it more,
this whole problem is only if you're drinking these pairs and then
you're going to go on a trip. So it's like a drinking
and driving problem. אבל בביתא *aval beveisa*, if you're just staying home
and getting drunk, then לא *lo*, it's not a problem. Presumably now,
I'm a little bit, you know, I'm joking when I say drink
and drive, but presumably again the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is always concerned
that when you go on a travel on a trip you'll be
you're more exposed to מזיקים *mazikin*, you know, the evil forces, you
know, the demonic forces and so on. So presumably these pairs, you
know, sort of make you more vulnerable, but as long as you're
staying home you're safe. אבל בביתא לא *aval beveisa lo*, guess this
person never heard that 90% of accidents happen within five miles of
the house. So anyway, לא *lo*. אמר רב זירא *amar Rav Zeira*,
ולמישן כצאת לדרך דמי *v'lemishan k'latzis laderech dami*. Ah, now this again
shows that we're not obviously translating it into contemporary medical terms. If
you want to take, if you want to go to sleep, then
that is a problem. That's as dangerous as going on the way.
Presumably, you know, you're asleep, your soul departs from you, you're more
in danger. So again, we would say sleep it off, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* say, if it were a concern again about being
drunk, but for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it's this מזיקים *mazikin* concern,
so going to sleep is like is dangerous like going on a
trip. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa, *amar Rav Papa*, ולבי הכסא
כצאת לדרך דמי *v'l'vei hakissei k'latzis laderech dami*. If you have to
leave the house to go to the outhouse, okay, which is presumably
what you might have to. do if you've been drinking a lot.
That's also a danger. That's like going on a trip. So it's
really like you just have to completely stay indoors. It's like another
type of לא יצא איש מפתח ביתו עד בוקר type of a
thing. ובביתו לא, u'v'beiso lo, so the גמרא Gemara says ובביתו לא,
u'v'beiso lo, in your house are you telling me it's not a
problem? So רבא, Rava, when רבא Rava would be drinking, מני כשורא,
manei kisurei, he would count the beams, meaning in order to keep
track of did he drink an even number or an odd number,
which number was he up to of his glasses of wine, he
would like say you know he'd look at that beam when he
was on an even, on when he was on an odd number,
and that beam when he was on an even number, so he'd
remember oh yeah my last cup I looked at that beam, so
now I can you know now I'm on even, so now I
have to drink another glass. Anyway he had a whole system of
keeping track of whether he was even and odds while he was
drinking presumably and staying home.
So that's רבא. Rava. ואביי כי הוה שתי, v'Abaye ki hava sheti,
when אביי Abaye would drink, חד כסא, chad kasa, he'd have one
cup then or an even number but one cup, ממטיא ליה אימיה,
mamatya lei imei, his mother, now it's not his mother, אביי Abaye,
actually both of his parents died,
his father before he was born, his mother when he was born,
and he was raised by a nursemaid. But the גמרא Gemara refers
to his nursemaid as his mother.
Some say אביי Abaye is an acronym for אשר בך ירחם יתום.
asher becha yerucham yasom. So that's a nice thought. I don't know
if that's true or not. But anyway, okay. אביי כי הוה שתי
חד כסא ממטיא ליה אימיה תרי כסא
בתרי ידא. Abaye ki hava sheti chad kasa mamatya lei imei terei
kasei bitrei yadei. So when he would be drinking one cup, his
nursemaid, his mother, you know his surrogate mother would be holding onto
two glasses for him to remind him that now he had to
drink two to stay with even. So when he said could I
have another glass of wine, she'd actually have two glasses already to
make sure that he would not get stuck at an even number,
yes.
I thought that two is okay
because the practical application to this today
is women lighting candles light two and then you go to five.
Interesting. Oh that's very interesting.
You light and you look at the candelabra they'll have five, you'll
never see four.
That's very interesting. I'd have to look into that because
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara right, the גמרא Gemara is the
opposite, the גמרא Gemara thinks that higher numbers are less of a
problem and two is definitely a problem. So
maybe the שמור וזכור shamor v'zachor you know saves you, that's like
you know so that's a freebie. I don't know. It's interesting I
have to look into it but in the גמרא Gemara the two
is a definite problem we'll see in a minute that higher multiples
might be less of a problem.
So the גמרא Gemara so you see that they were concerned even
at home. So the גמרא Gemara says אדם חשוב שאני, adam chashuv
shani, an important person is different. Now that's interesting because sometimes you
see this idea of אדם חשוב adam chashuv in the גמרא Gemara
to talk about a different type of sort of standard of behavior
but most often it's in terms of the way a person
acts in the public sphere and the way therefore the expectations people
have of this person that he's an אדם חשוב adam chashuv and
therefore how he has to be extra scrupulous about his behavior you
know like the גמרא Gemara speaks about you know I forget if
it was
אביי, רבא, Rava, whatever didn't even buy any food
on credit because it shouldn't look like they're getting benefit from the
fact that they're תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. They didn't even keep a
tab at the butcher you know and the גמרא Gemara speaks about
אדם חשוב. adam chashuv. So it concerns and here it's not
about the way you're perceived in society and what people will you
know the scrupulousness of your behavior in public, it's talking about in
private. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says you know basically that the מזיקין
mazikin are also more invested in hurting an אדם חשוב adam chashuv
than they are in hurting a lay person.
Right that's a good point, right, that's true and that's about the
type of whether drinking was considered an acceptable thing for her you
know that's true. So you're saying that maybe even at home there's
an aspect about your status.
Right in the פרק. perek. Right and look it doesn't mean you're
alone at home, you might still have a few friends or whatever
so it could be that that issue of אדם חשוב adam chashuv
remains even if you're in relative privacy.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla,
עשרה כוסות אין בהם משום זוגות, asara kosos ein bahem mishum zugos,
ten glasses now so this is the issue Rifka talked alluded to,
higher multiples of two might not be a problem. Once you're getting
into big numbers we don't think of them as doubles anymore. So
ten is not a problem. Okay, so if you're drinking a lot
just get till ten you'll be fine. So anyway עולא לטעמיה, Ulla
l'taamei, Ulla is according to his reasoning דאמר עולא ואמרי לה במתניתא
תנא, d'amar Ulla v'amrei lah be'masnisa tana, Ulla says and some say
it's a ברייתא, עשרה כוסות תקנו חכמים בבית האבל, asara kosos tiknu
chachamim b'veis ha'avel,
so that the rabbis established you know where we have a שבע
ברכות sheva brachos that follows בענטשן, bentching, the גמרא Gemara speaks about
particular ברכות brachos that were given for the מנחמים menachamim in a
בית אבל, beis avel, a ברוך אתה השם Baruch Atah Hashem and
ברכות brachos that were given in a בית אבל beis avel
specifically linked to after the meal
and within that structure we don't do that anymore, within that structure
there were actually specifically you were supposed to drink glasses of wine
after the meal in a בית האבל Beis Ha'avel actually up to
ten ten glasses of wine. And the גמרא Gemara basically speaks about
the fact that you know, if you're really you
know in צרה, tzara, so you drink a little it helps alleviate
it somewhat of course we know that alcohol is not a little,
we know alcohol is a depressant so it'll only have to work
temporarily. But it's interesting you know, going back to the גמרא Gemara
of יין ישמח לבב אנוש Yayin Yismach Levav Enosh that the גמרא
Gemara actually had a תקנה takana of ten glasses of wine in
the בית האבל. Beis Ha'avel. So therefore what עולא Ulla is saying
is that again similar to the idea of four glasses, חכמים chachamim
wouldn't be מתקן mesaken something that would have danger. So clearly it
must be that ten is is not a dangerous number. By the
time you hit ten you're safe. Yes.
Do we have a Talmudic tradition of saying blessings of בית האבל?
Beis Ha'avel?
Right. How could it be that we just don't do this?
But I know it's a complicated question yes.
But it's phenomenally powerful.
I agree. Yes.
How can the Jewish people what happened?
I don't you know I don't know I will I will I
will defer the question by saying that when we learn כתובות Kesubos
or ברכות Brachos when these issues come up we'll talk about it
some more. But it's a good point like right. I mean the
liturgy changes you know both adding new things and dropping things and
I agree I think that you know maybe the whole ritual of
the ten כוסות was you know there was a time when in
society that was like that you know impractical and and you know
excessive. But one still wonders. Right. And it gets forgotten but one
does wonder why some of the liturgy at least didn't remain which
also was you know part of that the ברכת המזון Birkas Hamazon
in בית האבל. Beis Ha'avel. Yes. So now the גמרא Gemara says
ואי סלקא דעתך עשרה כסי יש בהם משום זוגות ve-isalka da'atach asara
kosi yesh bahem mishum zugos and if ten was a problem of
pairs, היכי קיימי רבנן ותקנו מילתא דאיכא סכנה. heichi kaimei rabanan vetiknu
milta de-ika sakana. So how could they establish something that would lead
to a סכנה? sakana? Now תוספות Tosafos points out you know there
was another answer available what the גמרא Gemara said before about the
four כוסות which is ברכת המזון the כוס של ברכת המזון kos
shel Birkas Hamazon maybe doesn't count to to make it a problem
so you really have nine you know and therefore you're safe. But
anyway this is עולא'ס Ulla's position that ten isn't a problem. And
now we're going to keep on going down to see how big
of a number can we have that it's no longer a concern
of pairs. אבל תמניא יש בהם משום זוגות. aval tamanya yesh bahem
mishum zugos. According to עולא Ulla eight is still a problem. רב
חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא דאמרי תרווייהו Rav Chisda ve-Rabba bar Rav
Huna damrei tavaihu רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רבה בר רב הונא
Rabba bar Rav Huna say שלום לטובה מצטרף לרעה לא מצטרף. shalom
letovah mitztaref lera lo mitztaref.
שלום Shalom like this idea of ברכת המזון only combines for good.
שלום Shalom only combines for good not for bad. What does it
mean? It means the ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim right? יברכך השם וישמרך
Yevarechecha Hashem veyishmerecha יאר השם פניו אליך ויחנך ya'er Hashem panav eleicha
veyechuneka ישא השם פניו אליך וישם לך שלום. yisa Hashem panav eleicha
veyasem lecha shalom.
So שלום shalom is number seven. So your seventh כוס is considered
to be the כוס of שלום. shalom. Every time if you're even
not only in a תקנה takana of בית האבל Beis Ha'avel רק
סתם stam drinking at home one glass after another but seven is
שלום. shalom. So therefore that doesn't count against you. So when you
get to number eight so you could stop at seven it's not
like it didn't happen but it won't hurt you. So if you
get if you go from seven to eight then seven doesn't count
against you and then you're only at seven so you're safe. And
therefore any number afterwards you're safe cause you could always either count
seven or not whether it's in whether it's in your interest. So
once you have one of those variable numbers you can always exceed
it cause you can then choose cause then it will never it
it will count to help you and not against you. Okay.
So what does the גמרא Gemara mean לרעה לא מצטרף? lera lo
mitztaref?
It won't it won't add to create an an even number which
is a bad number. It'll add it'll combine to create a good
number so it'll get you at seven so you could stop there.
But if you go on and drink number eight it won't it
won't add to the group to get an even number you'll be
considered like you still just have seven. Okay. So that's what he
says. שלום לטובה מצטרף לרעה לא מצטרף. shalom letovah mitztaref lera lo
mitztaref. אבל שיתא יש בהם משום זוגות. aval shisha yesh bahem mishum
zugos. Six is a problem. רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו Rabba ve-Rav
Yosef damrei tavaihu רבה Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef say ויחנך
לטובה מצטרף לרעה לא מצטרף. veyechuneka letovah mitztaref lera lo mitztaref. How
about the middle middle part of ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim right? יאר
השם פניו אליך ויחנך ya'er Hashem panav eleicha veyechuneka that's number five.
So five won't hurt you. So either you could stop at five
or if you continue on then you could pretend it's not there
so five and any number after five you're safe. Okay. אבל ארבעה
יש בהם משום זוגות. aval arba yesh bahem mishum zugos. Four is
a problem. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו Abaye ve-Rava damrei tavaihu אביי and
רבא Rava say וישמרך veyishmerecha right
let's just go to the first part יברכך השם וישמרך Yevarechecha Hashem
veyishmerecha
לטובה מצטרף לרעה לא מצטרף. letovah mitztaref lera lo mitztaref. So by
the time you get to number three you're safe. Number three right
four won't anything after three you can stop and anything afterwards you
can choose whether to count number three or not so you'll always
be considered at an odd number so basically the only problem is
two. Now the רשב"ם Rashbam points out something important here and it's
sort of you know the obviously it's funny they're all going down
but if you take a look at the רשב"ם Rashbam he says
about one two three four five six seven lines down the wide
lines רבה ורב יוסף כמו שהיו הדורות זו אחר זו היו מקילין
בזוגות והולכין ופוחתין. Rabba ve-Rav Yosef kemoshehayu hadorot zu achar zu hayu
mekilin bezugot veholechin ufotchin. So he basically points out that this is
historical that the זוגות zugos issue became less and less of a
concern as time went on and therefore in a way he doesn't
exactly end. About 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 lines down
the wide lines, רבא ורב יוסף Rava v'Rav Yosef תמו שהיו הדורות
זו אחר זו היו מקילין בזוגות והולכין ופוחתין. tamu she-hayu ha-dorot zo
achar zo hayu mekilin bi-zugot v'holchin u-pochatin. So he basically points out
that this is historical, that the זוגות zugot issue became less and
less of a concern as time went on, and therefore in a
way he doesn't exactly say this, but he pretty much suggests it
that all this play with the ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim and using
it to say oh eight is a problem, six isn't a problem,
four isn't a problem, is a way to downplay the concern of
the זוגות zugot and to sort of say let's just get it
to a much smaller area of concern. Okay? So he sees it
that as historical. It should also be pointed out that this is
particularly a heightened concern in the בבלי Bavli and not in the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi and there's a, I think Dr. Elman has done work
on these sort of influences, Zoroastrian influence around these types of issues
about pairs and demons and how it makes you suspect to it
and so on. So it's a בבלי Bavli concern and it's a
concern that lessens as time goes along.
So can we then conclude that two is the only issue?
So according to אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava two is the only issue.
Okay.
Even worse even back at the time? What? Most of the מזיקין
mazikin were keeping up.
Right, exactly. Well, yes, exactly. What? One of? Changing perception led to
changing realities or vice versa. I was just telling my students that
there's a great statement, I forget who says it, but you know
the רמב"ם Rambam says that the only people, there's no such thing
as
שדים ומזיקין shedim u-mazikin and the גמרא Gemara didn't really mean it
and the only people who have believed in that were like fools
and children. And then, so he says this, and then, and then,
you know, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch like quoted in a particular
context and then the גר"א Gra writes in his comments on the
שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, he basically says, you know, the Greek philosophers
led רמב"ם Rambam astray and it's completely, he's completely wrong and of
course שדים ומזיקין shedim u-mazikin exist and I spoke to the head
שד shed and whatever we'll see that in the גמרא Gemara in
a minute. And then, you know, and he so he says you
know and of course they exist and the גמרא Gemara means what
it says. So somebody commented he says, you know when the רמב"ם
Rambam wrote there were no שדים shedim in the world, all of
the שדים shedim in the world, you know, disappeared. And then the
גר"א Gra came and he wrote רמב"ם Rambam is wrong and there
are שדים shedim and then they all came back.
You know it speaks about how our perception of reality and do
we experience שדים shedim or not has a lot to do with,
you know, with the sort of the perceptions we bring to the
world. Yes.
Does the גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachot say it's on purpose that
שדים shedim can attack two people but they can attack one?
Oh, well there is a גמרא Gemara that says that if you're
going on a trip you should definitely have another person with you
right because the שדים shedim want to get you when you're alone.
So it's interesting what you're asking is that that's not concerned about
the fact that there's a pair of people. Right. The גמרא Gemara
is never concerned with a pair of people. It's concerned with, you
know, doing things in multiples, but it's a good point that there
actually דווקא davka the גמרא Gemara speaks about having someone with you
so you're less susceptible. Yes.
Difference between
שדים ומזיקין?
shedim u-mazikin? That's a good question. I'm not the one to ask
about that. The גמרא Gemara is going to distinguish between מזיקין mazikin
and כשפים. kishufim. כשפים kishufim specifically acts of witchcraft that are done
to attack somebody by witches particularly women. We'll see. I mean the
גמרא Gemara. does also have male sort of warlocks but particularly emphasizes
women witches and that is going to come up. The difference between
מזיקין mazikin and שדים, shedim, I'm sure. I mean מזיקין mazikin very
much have the sense of only sort of injurious forces whereas שדים
shedim can be like powers that are, you know, that you can
sort of control and like the famous, you know, מדרשים midrashim that
I don't know if you grew up on, I grew up on
from the Jewish Press when they had that page that they had
in the middle where they had all these like children's stories or
whatever anyway and they had, you know, about שלמה Shlomo and the
שד shed he had doing all this work for him. Nobody else
read this growing up? What? שלמה ואשמדאי.
Shlomo v'Ashmedai. שלמה ואשמדאי. Shlomo v'Ashmedai.
That was the Jewish Press. That was the Jewish Press. I meant
the Jewish Press. חס ושלום chas v'shalom not the Jewish week, the
Jewish Press. Okay. Anyway. So שדים shedim presumably are more, are more
like, you know, I think that there tends to be an evil,
you know, fundamentally like an evil sort of dimension to them but
I think they can more be controlled whereas מזיקין mazikin I think
are just, you know, evil forces by themselves. Whether one is a
subset of the other that I don't know already. Okay, yes.
Joshua Trachtenberg's Jewish Magic and Superstition. Okay.
And what does he say? All right. All right. Let's take a
look. All right. ואזדא רבא לטעמיה. v'azda Rava l'taameih. Now by the
way you should remember אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava who are both saying
that you don't have to worry more than two. They were the
ones that were counting the beams and so on. So they still
felt that אדם חשוב adam chashuv maybe or something makes a difference
even for that. Anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ואזדא רבא לטעמיה. v'azda Rava l'taameih. רבא Rava
before the רבנן, you know, the rabbinic students would leave his house,
go home for a שבת Shabbos or something, he would see them
off and they'd have a drink before they would go and sometimes
they would drink four glasses and he'd still see them off. How
could he give them four glasses of wine before seeing them off?
So must be he felt that more than two is not a
problem. אף על גב דאיציק. af al gav d'itzik. Now, there was
a story that somebody actually left his house after four glasses of
wine and got hurt. אף על גב דאיציק רבא בר ליוואי. af
al gav d'itzik Rava bar Livai. And רבא בר ליוואי Rava bar
Livai once actually got hurt after leaving his house and drinking four
cups of wine. This is so I think, you know,
fascinating because how do you interpret right if you believe in מזיקין,
mazikin, you know, if you believe in מזיקין mazikin or you believe
in doubles and you... do something double and somebody gets hurt, obviously
you see that as proof that this was that this exposes you
to danger, whereas the nine times out of ten where nobody gets
hurt, then you were lucky, but the one time out of ten
where you did get hurt it was because of the concern of
the doubles, you know, the sort of assumptions you bring to it,
you know, the evidence that supports your thesis you pay attention to
and the rest you discard. So the גמרא Gemara says here רבא
Rava didn't believe that four was a problem. So how does he
do with the fact that רבא בר ליואי Rava bar Livai got
injured once? לא חש לה למלתא, Lo chash lah lemilsa, he wasn't
concerned about that, דאמר ההוא משום דאוספין בפרקא הוה. de-amar, ahu mishum
de-osfin be-pirka havei. That was cause he was such a נודניק nudnik
and he was always challenging me when I would give a דרשה.
drasha. That's why he got hurt! Not because I gave him four
glasses of wine! So it's very clear whatever, you know, the interpretations
you bring to the phenomenon explain what the cause of causal relationship
is. Yes, causal relationship is.
So never challenge the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva.
Well, yes, exactly. I mean the רשב"ם Rashbam says he embarrassed him
in public. But who knows? Maybe he was just asking an innocent
question and רבא Rava didn't have the answer. Yes, one more question.
Since
all of don't really have the idea of comparable comparison groups,
and yet there is something like that in תנ"ך, Tanach, in ספר
דניאל. Sefer Daniel.
Like doing
like
a control group. Right. But look what the גמרא Gemara is reflecting
is I think how a lot of people operate, you know, which
is that
they, especially if you have superstitions and whatnot, you pay attention to
the one time where there was some correspondence and you ignore all
the other evidence and you see that as proof that that was
because that this thing was done in a particular way, right? You
know? Just like this time did have comparison groups.
Right.
Yeah. Could you simply say a word about the word דאוספין? de-osvin?
Yeah, from the like מותבי, masvei, I'll ask you a question. Yeah,
he asked him questions. Yeah, he asked him questions during the שיעור
shiur and that you know upset him and embarrassed him. Alright, it's
pretty fascinating.
Ready for something more?
No? Okay, so now the גמרא says like this. All right. Now,
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, אמלי יוסף שידא, amli Yosef Shida,
now יוסף Yosef the שד shade said to me, so here we're
dealing with שדים, sheidim, right? אשמדאי מלכא דשידי, Ashmedai malka de-shidei, אשמדאי
Ashmedai the king of all the שדים, sheidim, ממוני הוא אכולהו זוגי.
memunei hu akulu zugei. He's the one. So here you see that
it's connecting it to שדים, sheidim, not מזיקין, mazikim, again I'm not
sure how distinct those categories are. He's the one that's in charge
of all the issues of pairs and, you know, basically the ability
to hurt people, you know, when they do things in pairs. ומלכא
לא איקרי מזיק. U-malka lo ikri mazik. And a king doesn't want
to be known as a, you know, as a destroyer, as a
damager. So basically he means, you know, it's not such a big
concern because ultimately the issue of pairs is something under the control
of the king שד shade and therefore it's not something that he's
going to really, you know, want to, you know, be he's not
going to, you know, he needs to protect his reputation. So therefore
you don't have to be so concerned about
pairs because he doesn't want to be known as a מזיק. mazik.
איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, some say the opposite. אדרבה. Adderaba. מלכא, Malka,
now some have the
גרסא girsa רתחנא הוא. ratchana hu. He's an angry king. Or just
מלכא, malka, a king. מאי דבעי עביד. Mai de-ba'i avid. A king
can do whatever the heck he wants. שהמלך פורץ גדר לעשות לו
דרך, She-hamelech poretz geder la'asos lo derech, because the הלכה, halacha, a
king can break through a fence to make a way, like you
know, he can totally overtake people's property. He ultimately gets to do
whatever he wants, as who is it in Mel Brooks? It's good
to be king, right? ואין מוחין בידו. Ve-ein mochin be-yado. And nobody
can stop him. So therefore he's going to feel free to hurt
people if they expose themselves with pairs. Okay. אמר רב פפא, Amar
Rav Papa, אמרי
לי, amri li, now we're talking about שדים sheidim talking to the
אמוראים. Amoraim. Note, so אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa so רב
פפא Rav Papa said, אמלי יוסף שידא. amli Yosef Shida. So יוסף
Yosef the שד shade said to me, בתרי קטלינן. be-trei katlinan. So
here again we have the שדים sheidim who are doing it. With
two, if somebody drinks just two, then I'll be able to kill
them. וארבעה ve-arba if they drink four, that's dangerous but not as
dangerous. לא קטלינן. Lo katlinan. I won't be able to kill them.
אבל בארבעה מזקינן, Aval be-arba mazakinan, I'll be able to damage them.
בתרי Be-trei if you drink just two, בין בשוגג בין במזיד, bein
be-shogeg bein be-mezid, whether you're doing it aware or unaware, you're not,
you know, whether you're like, you know, you know it's a pair,
you know it's two and you don't care, "I don't believe in
this nonsense," it doesn't, you know, that's מזיד. mezid. It won't matter
either way, you're exposing yourself to danger. בארבעה, Be-arba, four, the bigger
the number the less it's focused on as a pair. In that
case, במזיד אין, be-mezid in, you're only exposing yourself if you do
it willingly. בשוגג לא, Be-shogeg lo, not if you're unaware.
ואישתלי דאקרי ונפק, Ve-ishtali de-ikrei ve-nafik, מאי תקנתיה? mai takantei? Now somebody
forgot, he drank a pair, two cups of wine, and now he
left the bar and he's walking home. What's he supposed to do?
He can't get a third glass anymore, bar's closed, he's a mile
from home, a mile from the bar, what's he supposed to do?
לינקוט זקפא דידא דימינא בידא
דשמאלא. Linchis zakfa de-yada de-yamina be-yada de-smala. Hold the thumb of your
right hand in your left hand. וזקפא דשמאלא בידא דימינא. Ve-zakfa de-smala
be-yada de-yamina. The thumb of your left hand in your right hand.
You do this. right? If they like, right? Got that? Okay. ונימא
הכי ve-neima hachi and say the following. So now we get to,
as we know, in the number of places, particularly in ברכות Brachos
or whatever, we have these types of chants and incantations that are
supposed to protect you against the מזיקים and שדים. sheidim. So say
the following thing. אנתון ואנא
התלתא. atun va-ana hatlasa. You and I that makes three. So I
guess the drinks that I drank plus me gets us to an
odd number. So therefore I'm safe. ואי שמיע ליה דאמר ve-ishmeia lei
de-amar and then if he hears a voice saying, whether it's a
voice from the heaven, from the ether or whether it's actually a
person saying it, doesn't matter. If he hears some voice that responds
and says, אנתון ואנא הארבעה atun va-ana ha-arba'a but me and you
that makes four, meaning I guess the שד sheid now made it
an even number. לימא ליה leima lei say back to it אנתון
ואנא החמישה atun va-ana ha-chamisha me and you is five. ואי שמיע
ליה דאמר ve-ishmeia lei de-amar אנתון ואנא השישה atun va-ana ha-shisha and
then if he hears it respond you and I make six. לימא
ליה leima lei אנתון ואנא השבעה atun va-ana ha-shiva you and I
make seven. והוה עובדא va-hava uvda there was a case עד מאה
וחד ad mea ve-chad it went back and forth until the guy
got up to 101 ופקע שידא u-paka sheida and then the שד
sheid burst. So that basically, so if you're able to have the
perseverance, you can ultimately protect yourself and even destroy the שד sheid
apparently with this incantation. Wait a minute. אמר רב פפא
before he's told over this story, right?
Did the שד sheid keep on increasing in size until it...
Oh, that's what you mean, the שד sheid keeps on
growing, maybe.
Yeah, back to the king, about protesting the king. It's not that
kings are getting... they're acting to be protested against all the time
by the נביאים. nevi'im.
Yeah, that's true. What can I tell you? He means he has
a legal right and
yeah, story of the שד sheid and this was a story for
the king.
Right, well, that's what the רמב"ם Rambam says. That's what רמב"ם Rambam
says, right. And for the middle page of the Jewish Press. Okay,
so אמר מימר amar Meimar אמרה לי רישתינא
הדין דנשי כשיפנייתא amra li Rishtina hadin de-nashei kashfanyasa so said
to me Rishtina, the head matron of the women witches, of the
women who do witchcraft. So apparently she was the power that they
worshipped or whatever that they drew upon. האי מן דפגע hai man
de-paga sort of like the parallel to the יוסף Yosef of the
head שד. sheid. האי מן דפגע hai man de-paga but now it's
about witchcraft, about making yourself suspect to people that are doing
witchcraft, vulnerable. האי מן דפגע בנשי כשיפנייתא hai man de-paga be-nashei kashfanyasa
if you bump into a group, a coven, is that what it's
called? A coven of witches, right? So sort of like a Hamlet
scene there, not Hamlet, a Macbeth scene. Okay, נימא הכי neima hachi
say the following. So חרי חמימי chari chamimi hot excrement, boiling excrement,
בדיקולא דזיא be-dikula de-zaya in a torn basket, לפומייכו le-pumeichu should be
put into your mouths, נשי דחרשייא nashei de-charshaya you women witches. קרח
קרחייכי kerach karchaichi פרח פרחייכי perach perchaichi
so that could just be nonsense words, but the רשב"ם Rashbam says
it means bald, you said your hair should be bald, apparently they
used their hair, their head for certain types of potions or whatever,
brew, and פרח פרחייכי perach perchaichi means also they use different types
of,
one way he reads it is either it's the name of some
type of also instrument they used or it means pieces of bread
that they used in the witchcraft, that should blow away. Okay, so
your hair should fall out, your bread should blow away.
איבדור תבלינייכו ibdur tavlineichu your brews, yeah brews, your potions,
your fragrances should be scattered. פרחא
זיקא למיריקא parcha zika le-morika the wind should blow
away the saffron, חדתא דנקיטו chadata de-nakitu the new saffron that you
are holding onto. Again, the various sort of
ingredients for your
potion. נשי כשיפנייתא nashei kashfanyasa women who do witchcraft, עד דחנני וחננכי
ad de-chanani ve-chananechi
as long as I was taken care upon
myself and you had care on me, לא אתיתי לגו lo asisi
le-go I would not, I never came into your midst. השתא דאתיתי
לגו hashta de-asisi le-go now that I've come into your midst, קר
חנני וחננכי kar chanani ve-chananechi
so you have
cooled off your favor to me or my favor has cooled off,
basically now I'm exposed to your risk, the good luck I had
until now is no longer around that I've been exposed to you.
Okay now the גמרא makes a very, so okay, I have nothing
to say about that. But as we do know, look, women really
it was a way in which women were demonized in ancient society,
the assumption of women and witchcraft.
Right after במערבא? be-ma'arava?
Right, sure, I mean Salem witch trials and so. במערבא be-ma'arava in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael לא קפדי אזוגי. lo kapdi a-zugei. Like very
important four words right there. How about an acknowledgment that this was
a בבל Bavel concern and not an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael concern
and how the society you're
in might impact your these types of It reduces your perception of
these issues.
Because that would mean even two.
Yeah, they completely dismiss this concern. רב דימי מנהרדעא, Rav Dimi mi'Nehardea,
רב דימי Rav Dimi from נהרדעא Nehardea קפיד אפילו ארושמא דחביתא. kapid
afilu a'rushma de'chavita. He was concerned even on the marks you make
on a barrel, like if you're selling wine from a barrel or
you're drinking from a barrel and you make like you know little
hash marks to count how many glasses you've you know or ounces
you've sold, he would be careful that it would always be an
odd number, not an even number, even if he wasn't drinking in
pairs. ההוא עובדא פקעה חביתא, Hahu uvda paka'a chavita, and then there
was a case where there was an even number and the barrel
burst. So clearly you see that, you know, clearly you see that
the pairs led to the bursting of the barrel because there was
an even number of marks on the barrel and then the barrel
burst. כללא דמילתא, Klala d'milta, now the Gemara makes again sort of
like this statement I made about the שדים shedim you know disappeared
and came back, although the Gemara isn't exactly making it from this
psychological perspective, but the next line is very interesting. כללא דמילתא, Klala
d'milta, the rule is, כל דקפיד קפדי בהדיה, Kol de'kapid kapdi bahadei,
anybody that is overly careful, the Rashbam says anyone that's overly careful
about these issues, so the שדים shedim will pay attention to him
and you are more exposing yourself. ודלא קפיד לא קפדי בהדיה, U'delo
kapid lo kapdi bahadei, but if you don't care, they won't care
about you and they'll leave you alone. So now the Rashbam says
obviously this could not mean totally, that if you completely ignored it
you wouldn't have any danger because then why is the Gemara discussing
it? It should not be in the Gemara, the Gemara should do
us all a favor and just not discuss it and then we
won't be מקפיד makpid and they won't be מקפיד makpid on us.
So he reads it in a sense of if you're overly מקפיד
makpid then you're exposing yourself. If you're not מקפיד makpid then you're
minimizing the exposure, but obviously there's a minimum amount of care that
every person has to do. But again from a psychological perspective, you
know it's very it's fascinating, right? If you're always concerned about it,
you're going to be experiencing you know you're going to be experiencing
it a lot. And if you ignore it you won't experience it.
Yeah, we'll go around this way, go ahead.
Like when you make those marks to count, after the fourth you
cross it out with a slash.
So then it makes it five. Right, exactly the way we do
it, right? So
maybe that comes from that, yeah, I don't know, maybe just as
an easy way of you know adding up five, but right, but
yeah, I guess.
It's just as much psychological as maybe sociological that it's a way
to shut down the conversation. Right. If somebody wants to have long
conversations about שדים. shedim.
Right. Well if you care about שדים shedim this is very important,
but if you don't.
I think it's a nice perspective, right. Yes, though.
No, no, no, I'm just trying to stay safe here.
Alright, so I just want to read the next few words because
essentially what the Rashbam says, it says what the Gemara said, ומיהו
למיחש מיהא בעי. U'mihu lemichash miha ba'ei. Right, exactly. ומיהו למיחש מיהא
בעי, U'mihu lemichash miha ba'ei, so this is again the point I
just made. The Rashbam emphasizes it but it's really in the
Gemara, that even if you're not מקפיד makpid and they won't be
so מקפיד makpid on you, a certain amount of concern is appropriate.
Okay. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar, when
רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said,
now now again notice he's coming from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where
they're not מקפיד makpid on it. So here's what he said. שתי
ביצים ושתי אגוזים, Shtei beitzim u'shtei egozim, two eating two eggs or
eating two nuts, שתי קישואים Shtei kishu'im or two gourds, ודבר אחר,
U'davar acher, and there's one other thing. So he basically said the
whole idea of pairs applied to four foods and that's it. Eggs,
gourds, nuts, and one other thing, he forgot which one the other
one was. הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe Mi'Sinai, now that's pretty strong
used to word for this. The הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe Mi'Sinai
is used at times more metaphorically. There's a whole discussion what's her
name Shalott-Fun Roberts wrote a whole article on הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
L'Moshe Mi'Sinai and about its way in which its use evolved from
the time of the תנאים Tanaim to the אמוראים Amoraim to the
later period. And anyway but clearly in this case it's used just
meaning that this is an ancient tradition that there are these four
foods that are only these four foods are a problem. ומסתפקא להו
לרבנן מאי ניהו דבר אחר, U'mistapka lehu l'rabbanan mai nihu davar acher,
but the Rabbis just didn't know which number four was because the
three we knew, we didn't know number four. וגזרו רבנן בכולהו זוגי
משום דבר אחר. Vegazru rabbanan be'kulehu zugei mishum davar acher. So all
of this concern of pairs about everything, particularly we're finding it about
wine. You notice all the Gemara before was about wine. We're about
to get into other issues. But according to him, the first three
weren't wine, the first three were foods, and the only concern about
all this pairs was just because we didn't know what number four
was. Now again, this is maybe a way for them to be,
you know at least also this is through the eyes of the
בבלי, Bavli, who knows who knows what he really said, maybe he
just ended at the דבר אחר, davar acher, maybe he said the
whole thing was nonsense, but this was the report coming from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael where they fundamentally did not care about the זוגות.
zugot. And the בבלי Bavli is interpreting it as all it's all
חומרא chumra or even you know because we don't know what one
of them was.
Just this idea according to that is snakes and ladders. Exactly, they're
aren't and if there are maybe it's this food and...
And and of course the irony of juxtaposing it to the issue
of דכל דקפיד. d'kol de'kapdi. If you're not מקפיד makpid on worrying
about what the fourth one is, that's a big הקפדה. hakpada. That's
a big הקפדה, hakpada, worrying everything might be this what they
I'm מקפיד! makpid! Right. Okay. והא דאמרן עשרה, Ve'ha de'amran asara, תמניא
ושישא אין בהם משום זוגי. tamnya v'shisha ein bahem mishum zugei. So
now the Gemara is gonna step back, because now it ended sort
of with almost a downplay. downplaying of the concern of זוגות *zugot*,
לא מקפיד makpid. *lo makpid*, everything's a big חומרא *chumra*. It says
don't think we can totally dismiss it. When we say things like
ten, eight, six, four are not a pair problem of pairs, לא
אמרן אלא לעניין מזיקין mazikin *lo amran ela l'inyan mazikin*. That's only
to expose yourself to מזיקין *mazikin*. Again, notice the גמרא *Gemara* earlier
said שדים shedim *sheidim* and here it's saying מזיקין *mazikin*. אבל לעניין
כשפים *aval l'inyan keshafim*, but to make yourself vulnerable to witchcraft, אפילו
טובא נמי חיישינן *afilu tuvei nami chaishinan*, even if you have a
high multiple, 10, 20, 36, any pairs is a danger, but that's
only in a place where there are actually witches who are doing
witchcraft as opposed to מזיקין *mazikin*, presumably מזיקין *mazikin* are everywhere, but
so you don't have to worry about higher numbers than two for
the מזיקין *mazikin*, but if it's a place that you're concerned about
כשפים *keshafim*, then it's a concern. כי הא *ki ha*, now we'll
have a story, דההוא גברא gavra. *d'hahu gavra*, a certain man דגרשה
לדביתהו *d'garsha l'dveitehu*, he divorced his wife, אזלה אינסבא לחנואה *azla insava
l'chanu'ah*, she went and she married an innkeeper who also would serve
wine. כל יומא הוה אתי ושתי חמרא *kol yoma hava ati v'shati
chamra*, he would go, the ex-husband would go to the inn and
every day he'd drink wine there. הויא קא עבדא ליה כשפים *hava
ka avda leh keshafim*, and she would be in the back, you
know, in the kitchen or something, and she saw that her husband
was there and she would be, you know, making sort of witchcraft
against him. ולא קא מהניא ליה *v'lo ka mahanya leh*, and it
didn't do any good because he was always careful to drink odd
numbers of cups of wine. ולא קא מהניא ביה משום דהוה מזהר
בנפשיה בזוגא *v'lo ka mahanya beh mishum d'hava mizaher b'nafsheh b'zuga*, he
was very careful about pairs. יומא חד אשתי טובא *yoma chad ishti
tuvei*, one day he drank a lot, ולא הוה ידע כמה שתי
*v'lo hava yada kama shati*, he didn't know how many cups he'd
drunk, he lost count. עד שיתסר *ad shitsar*, until 16, הוה ציל
*hava tzil*, he was clear-minded ומזהר בנפשיה *v'mizaher b'nafsheh*, and was careful,
maybe careful that he knew whether he was on an even or
an odd number or just meant careful in terms of other things
that might expose him to this witchcraft. מכאן ואילך לא הוה ציל
*mikan v'eilach lo hava tzil*, after 16 he was having a laugh
and revel, they watered their wine down a lot, but okay, after
16 he was not clear, ולא מזהר בנפשיה *v'lo mizaher b'nafsheh*, he
wasn't being careful, ואפיק ליה בזוגא *v'afik leh b'zuga*, and again maybe
and he went out with pairs, meaning he ended with a pair,
with an even number, not an odd number, he wasn't paying attention.
כי הוה אזיל *ki hava azil*, as he was and so she
now maybe had thrown, you know, had put some hex on him
that he was now exposed to it, it hadn't had an effect
yet, but he was now exposed to it because he had drunk
an even number. כי הוה אזיל *ki hava azil*, as he was
walking on the way leaving the bar, פגע ביה ההוא טייעא *paga
beh hahu taya*, a certain
wandering merchant bumped into him, it's often an Arab is seen, you
know, as a nomad bumped into him, and they're often seen to
have a lot of wisdom about knowledge about this type of stuff.
אמר ליה *amar leh*, and he says to him, גברא קטילא הוא
דאזיל הכא *gavra ktila hu d'azil hacha*, I see a dead man
walking, right? There's a new movie like that or a book like
that, whatever, a game, dead man walking. I see a dead man
walking here. אזיל חבקיה לדיקלא *azil chavkeh l'dikla*, he went, he grabbed
onto a palm tree, like, you know, to bemoan his fate or
something. צבח דיקלא ופקע הוא *tzavach dikla u'paka hu*, and the palm
tree cried out and he burst, like the birch burst. Now who
burst? Our גרסא *girsa* is ופקע הוא *u'paka hu*, he burst. Some
say ופקע דיקלא *u'paka dikla*, that the palm tree burst, somehow the
hex managed to transfer to the palm tree. Okay, but anyway, there
you see that if you drink pairs even a high number, 16,
you're exposing yourself to witchcraft. אמר רב אבירא *amar rav avira*, said
Rav Avira, קרות וככרות *karot v'kikarot*, plates and loaves of bread, אין
בהם משום זוגות *ein bahem mishum zugot*. Plates and loaves of bread
do not have a problem of זוגות *zugot*, okay, which mean that
if plates, so what do the plates mean? I mean, so the
רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*, I mean the ככרות *kikarot* is just loaves of
bread themselves. The רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says אם אכל שתי קערות תבשיל
*im achal shtei k'arot tavshil*, it means that you ate two plates
of food. Okay, so that doesn't have משום זוגא *mishum zuga*, why?
כללא דמילתא *klala d'milta*, the rule is, כל שגמרו בידי אדם *kol
she'gemaru bidei adam*, אין בהם משום זוגות *ein bahem mishum zugot*. If
it is done by, if it's made by people, like bread is
more seen as manufactured, I mean I don't know, wine is manufactured
too, but maybe that's seen as fundamentally it's the juice and its
natural form that was left to ferment as opposed to a cooked
dish, as opposed to bread. So things that are more human, you
know, seen as human creations,
so then that's not a problem of זוגות *zugot*. כל שגמרו בידי
שמים *kol she'gemaru bidei shamayim*, I lost my place, גמרו בידי שמים
*gemaru bidei shamayim*, במילי מיני דמיכל *b'mili minei d'michal*, so if it's
something that's done by heaven and it's foodstuffs, then חיישינן *chaishinan*, we're
concerned about the זוגות *zugot* concern. חנות *chanut*, if you have a
bar, אין בהם משום זוגות *ein bahem mishum zugot*. If you drink
in a bar, it's not a problem, which is good. So now
if you drink at home, it's not a problem if you stay
at home, the גמרא *Gemara* said before, and if you drink in
a bar, it's not a problem. So why if you drink at
a bar is it not a problem? So the רשב"ם *Rashbam* says
because then every new glass of wine is a new decision. I
don't know, I guess depends on how people go into a bar.
So the רשב"ם *Rashbam* also says if it means if you drink
two glasses at two different bars, it's not a problem, they don't
combine. Okay, but one explanation is even two glasses at the same
bar, you're always making a new decision. Of course, how about the
story before about the witchcraft? So he says that was different, he
says that because that was a witchcraft that was directed at him.
This is a more generic concern of זוגות for the מזיקין not
necessarily directed witchcraft. Okay. Now, where were we?
So bars don't have the problem, it's not considered like you know
like set drinking, it's all considered ad hoc type of drinking.
אין בהם משום זוגות נמלך אין בהם משום זוגות. ein bahem mishum
zugos nimlach ein bahem mishum zugos. If you make a decision to
have another glass, that's seen as a new act. If you weren't
planning on having multiple glasses. So that's not a problem. אורח אין
בו משום זוגות. ore'ach ein bo mishum zugos. If you have a
guest and you give your guest multiple glasses, it's not a problem
because again, the guest doesn't know if you're going to give him
another glass, so each glass is a new glass and is separate.
Again, the גמרא before just assumed that because it talked about Rava
giving his student, you know again, maybe that was different, maybe there
was a practice for them to always have multiple glasses of wine,
not exactly the same as a guest that doesn't know that you're
going to give him another glass of wine, but you see the
גמרא more and more, you know, cutting back on the areas of
concern that you have to worry about this. Okay. אשה אין בה
משום זוגות. isha ein ba mishum zugot. This ties into אשה חשובה
isha chashuva before. דאשה חשובה חיישינן, di-isha chashuva chashinan, right? What we
spoke about a woman not doing הסיבה, haseiba, I sent you out
that interesting thing about practices in Roman society where women not only
would not recline, but there was a significant period in Roman society
where it was inappropriate for women to drink wine, which softened over
time. So here in a way I think you see that reflected,
right? A woman drinking wine is not seen as a normal type
of a drinking. And therefore, it's not this concern, you know, every
occurrence maybe is considered an exception. And therefore they don't combine for
pairs or the whole thing isn't normal drinking like drinking in a
bar, you know, is not the same as a קביעות kevi'us drinking
at home. But if it's an important woman, a woman of stature,
then it's more acceptable for her to drink
wine, it is a more normal thing and that is a concern.
אמר רב חיננא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Chinena brei deRav Yehoshua,
so Rav Chinena the son of Rav Yehoshua says, אספרגוס, ispargus, well
guess what that is, right? Presumably asparagus.
מצטרף לטובה ואין מצטרף לרעה. mitztaref letova ve'ein mitztaref lera. So this
was a type of a drink that they had, this asparagus drink,
that was a health drink, something that they drink specifically for their
health. And this is saying that if you are having this type
of a thing, then again it won't because it's a good it's
good, it's done for your health, it won't create a problem of
pairs. So like the other כוס של ברכה, other types of things
which are seen that it'll end you on an odd number, but
if you go beyond that, it won't create an even number, you
can always say it doesn't count because it's considered like a good
כוס, yes, Charlie.
The Steinzaltz says it is a drink prepared from cabbage soaked in
wine or some other alcoholic beverage.
Right, so that's not actually asparagus per se.
Although the Greek word he says it's from is isparagus.
Right. So the רשב"ם says רגילין היו לשתותה בכל בוקר לרפואה קודם
אכילה. regilin hayu lishtosa bechol boker lerefu'ah kodem achila. Okay. והלכך מצטרף.
vehilkach mitztaref. Now what would it be מצטרף mitztaref to? Other glasses
of this asparagus drink? Or would it be מצטרף mitztaref. to wine?
We're going to talk about combining drinks of different types with one
another in a moment.
Okay. I should also point out it's interesting, not directly related to
our גמרא well somewhat related actually, that, you know, the whole question
about do you have to accept the authority of חז"ל Chazal when
it comes to like medical matters, health matters. And already some of
the גאונים Geonim were saying that, you know, you don't, that our
רפואה refu'ah is different, sometimes they use the idea of נשתנו הטבע,
nishtanu hateva, the nature has changed, the, you know, the natural laws
have changed. But basically you don't have to accept the authority of
חז"ל Chazal in medical matters. And one of the places this comes
up is there's a book called the ערוך, Aruch, which is a
dictionary written by רב נתן בעל הערוך, Rav Natan Ba'al Ha'Aruch, I
think in the ninth
century in Rome. Trying to remember whether it was ninth century, tenth,
maybe tenth. Maybe tenth century. Anyway, and he gives explanations of words
in the גמרא. Interestingly, because he's in Rome he often gives, you
know, the Greek when things have a Greek basis, he knew it,
he knows it, but he also quotes what the גאונים's Geonim interpretations
of this are. And in that dictionary under the word asparagus, he
discusses this medical drink and how the גמרא says how it's healthy,
whatever, and there he says, quotes the גאונים Geonim who say you
don't have to go by the גמרא in medical matters. So it's
interesting that that's one of the early places that that's pointed out
and again interesting in the context of the גמרא's concern here about
the whole issue around pairs and שדים even, you know, seems more
even more unrelated to our reality than their medical issues.
Yes, and contemporary halakhic writings about this issue, there is a position
that references the idea that the medical physician that should attend to
a person as a מומחה mumche in certain matters should be a
ירא שמים Yerei Shamayim MD. Uh-huh. And is that a modern and
contemporary
combination of yeah, I don't know.
No, I think that has to do with other things, you know,
with גמרות. Gemaras. I mean, I don't know if it has to
do with attitudes towards non-Jews. I don't know if it has to
do with issues when questions come up about שבת Shabbos and יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know, נדה Niddah questions. I don't know. You
know, but I think yeah, that's a much more
and I don't know, you know, and yeah,
that's much less based. I'm anyway, yeah.
Whoever holds that position has to assume that secular education is permitted.
What?
Oh I see. Okay, anyway, let's continue. All right, I'm just trying
to see if I can pull up this ערוך. Aruch. Anyway, okay.
מצטרף לטובה ואי מצטרף לרעה. mistaref letova ve'ei mistaref lera. So you
can use it to get you an odd number, but not to
get you, but not to get you an even number. אמר רבינא
משמיה דרבא. Amar Ravina mishmei de'Rava. רבינא Ravina said in the name
of רבא. Rava. Remember רבא Rava was the one that was said
anymore than two isn't a problem. זוגי לחומרא. zugei lechumra. That
if you have a ספק. safek. I got lost track. I don't
know if I had an even number or an odd number. What
should I do? Should I drink another glass of wine or not?
So are you מחמיר machmir or מיקל meikel if you don't know
if you're up to an even or an odd number? לחומרא. lechumra.
הספק hasafek you're מחמיר, machmir, meaning you have to drink another glass
of wine. ואמרי לה זוגי לקולא. ve'amrei lah zugei lekula. And some
say you're lenient. Now what's the issue? So the רשב"ם says well
if you're drinking this other glass just out of ספק, safek, so
if you were up to an odd number it wouldn't combine, because
מצטרף לטובה מצטרף לרעה לא מצטרף. mistaref letova mistaref lera lo mistaref.
That would be the approach of לחומרא. lechumra. The approach of לקולא
lekula is show that you're not מקפיד. makpid Going back to that
theme. If you're not מקפיד you're in a better situation also. Okay.
אמר
רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. Said רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. תרי חמרא
וחד
דשיכרא לא מצטרפי. trei chamra vechad deshichra lo mitztarfe. This is different
types of drinks. Two glasses of wine and one of beer don't
combine. תרי דשיכרא trei deshichra to get you into the odd zone
so you still got to drink another glass of wine. תרי דשיכרא
וחד דחמרא, trei deshichra vechad dechamra, if you however had two of
beer and one of wine, then you're safe. מצטרפי, mitztarfe, that does
get you. What's the difference? וסימנך זה הכלל כל המחובר לו מן
החמור ממנו טמא מן הקל ממנו טהור. vesimanecha zeh haklal kol hamuchbar
lo min hachamur mimenu tamei min hakal mimenu tahor. So now according
to halakhic source, if you're something is a hybrid fabric. Different fabrics
will cause will be susceptible for טומאה tumah in different sizes. The
more important the fabric, the smaller the size it can be to
be considered an important garment or a piece of a garment to
become טמא. tamei. Like they have silk and you have and you
have burlap. Okay, a small much smaller piece of silk is susceptible
to טומאה tumah than a piece of burlap. So let's say you've
got silk a little bit less than the right size and you
have sewn onto it a piece of burlap. Obviously that's not חשוב
chashuv because it's a lesser issue it's a lesser thing, it's not
מצטרף. But let's say you have a piece of burlap that's a
little bit less than the right size and you have sewn into
it a little piece of silk. That will combine because that gives
it more that a more important thing does combine. So, if you
have two glasses of wine a less important thing beer won't combine.
If you have two glasses of beer a more important thing wine
will combine. Okay we have to end very soon because it's Tuesday
so we have to clear the room a little earlier. Let's just
read one more thing. Okay. אמר רב נחמן אמר רב, Amar Rav
Nachman amar Rav, so said רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name
of רב. תרי קמי תכא וחד אטכא מצטרפי. trei kammei takka vechad
attei takka mitztarfe. If you have two glasses of wine before the
dish, before the meal, and one during the meal, that combines. חד
מקמי תכא ותרי אטכא chad mikmei takka vetrei attei takka and then
you're safe. One before the meal and two during the meal לא
מצטרפי. lo mitztarfe. That doesn't combine. So again, you know, sort of
some issue about which is more important. מתקיף לה רב משרשיא. Matkif
lah Rav Mesharshiya. רב משרשיא Rav Mesharshiya challenged this. אטו אנן לתיקוני
תכא קבעינן? atu anan letikunei takka kabeinan? Are we trying to fix
the the dish, the plate? לתיקוני גברא קבעינן. letikunei gavra kabeinan. We're
trying to fix you the person. וגברא מתקן וקאי. vegavra mitkan vekaye.
And you drank three glasses. It's a funny phrase but Briskers should
love this. Is it about the חפצא cheftza of the plate? It's
about the גברא. He drank three glasses. But again it's like funny
because apparently we're talking about whether they're similar types of drinks, but
he's basically saying who the heck cares? You drank three glasses, you
should be safe. So, one more line. דכולי עלמא וגברא מתקן וקאי.
dechulei alma vegavra mitkan vekaye. דכולי עלמא תרי אטכא וחד לבתר תכא
לא מצטרפי. dechulei alma trei attei takka vechad lebathar takka lo mitztarfe.
But everybody agrees that two during the meal and one after don't
combine and you are susceptible to problems and we will pick up
with this theme tomorrow. קדיש דרבנן. Kaddish derabbanan. Oh yeah we have
a מנין. minyan.